Both myself and my brother
كلانا انا و أخي
belong to the under 30 demographic,
ننتمي إلى الفئة العمرية تحت الـ 30،
which Pat said makes 70 percent,
وقالت بات ان هذا يشكل 70 في المئة،
but according to our statistics
ولكن وفقا لاحصاءاتنا
it makes 60 percent of the region's population.
هذا يشكل 60 في المئة من سكان المنطقة.
Qatar is no exception to the region.
قطر ليست استثناء في المنطقة.
It's a very young nation led by young people.
انها أمة فتية جدا بقيادة الشباب.
We have been reminiscing about the latest technologies
كنا نستذكر أحدث التقنيات
and the iPods,
و اجهزة اي بود،
and for me the abaya,
وبالنسبة لي العباءة،
my traditional dress that I'm wearing today.
زينا التقليدي الذي أرتديه اليوم.
Now this is not a religious garment,
الآن هذا ليس زي ديني،
nor is it a religious statement.
كما أنها ليست علامة على التدين.
Instead, it's a diverse cultural statement
بدلا من ذلك، انها تبين التنوّع الثقافي
that we choose to wear.
الذي اخترنا ارتداءه.
Now I remember a few years ago,
الآن أنا أتذكر قبل سنوات قليلة،
a journalist asked Dr. Sheikha, who's sitting here,
سأل احد الصحفيين الدكتورة شيخة، التي تجلس هنا،
president of Qatar University --
رئيسة جامعة قطر -
who, by the way, is a woman --
التي، هي بالمناسبة، امرأة -
he asked her whether she thought
سألها ما اذا كانت تعتقد
the abaya hindered or infringed her freedom in any way.
ان العباءة اعاقت أو أعاق حريتها بأي شكل من الأشكال.
Her answer was quite the contrary.
وكان جوابها على العكس تماما.
Instead, she felt more free,
بدلا من ذلك، شعرت بحرية اكثر،
more free because she could wear whatever she wanted
أكثر حرية، لأنها يمكن أن تلبس ما أرادت
under the abaya.
تحت العباءة.
She could come to work in her pajamas and nobody would care.
قالت انها يمكن ان تأتي للعمل في منامتها ولا أحد سيهتم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Not that you do; I'm just saying.
ليس ما تفعله، وأنا أقول ذلك فقط.
My point is here, people have a choice --
ومن وجهة نظري هنا، الناس لديهم خيار -
just like the Indian lady could wear her sari
مثلما يمكن للسيدة ارتداء ساريها الهندي
or the Japanese woman could wear her kimono.
أو يمكن للمرأة اليابانية ارتداء الكيمونو.
We are changing our culture from within,
نعمل على تغيير ثقافتنا من الداخل،
but at the same time
ولكن في نفس الوقت
we are reconnecting with our traditions.
نحن مع اعادة ربط تقاليدنا.
We know that modernization is happening.
نحن نعرف ان التحديث يحدث.
And yes, Qatar wants to be a modern nation.
و نعم، قطر تريد ان تكون دولة حديثة.
But at the same time
ولكن في نفس الوقت
we are reconnecting and reasserting our Arab heritage.
نحن نعيد الارتباط ونؤكد اهمية تراثنا العربي.
It's important for us to grow organically.
انه من المهم بالنسبة لنا أن ننمو طبيعيا.
And we continuously make the conscious decision
ونأخذ باستمرار قرارات واعية
to reach that balance.
لتحقيق هذا التوازن.
In fact, research has shown
في الواقع، أظهرت الأبحاث
that the more the world is flat,
أنه كلما كان العالم اكثر تسطحا،
if I use Tom Friedman's analogy,
إذا كنت تستخدم القياس توم فريدمان،
or global,
أو عالميا،
the more and more people are wanting to be different.
كلما زادت رغبة الناس في أن يكونوا مختلفين.
And for us young people,
وبالنسبة لنا الشباب،
they're looking to become individuals
الذين يتطلعون ليصبحوا متفردين
and find their differences amongst themselves.
ويجدون اخلافاتهم فيما بينهم.
Which is why I prefer the Richard Wilk analogy
هذا هو السبب لكوني أفضّل قياسا يلك ريتشارد
of globalizing the local
في عولمة المحلية
and localizing the global.
وإضفاء الطابع المحلي على الصعيد العالمي.
We don't want to be all the same,
نحن لا نريد أن نكون كلنا متشباهين،
but we want to respect each other and understand each other.
ولكننا نريد أن نحترم بعضنا البعض ونفهم بعضنا البعض.
And therefore tradition becomes more important,
وبالتالي التقاليد تصبح أكثر أهمية،
not less important.
ليس أقل أهمية.
Life necessitates a universal world,
الحياة تستلزم وجود عالم كوني،
however, we believe in the security
ومع ذلك، فإننا نعتقد في أمن
of having a local identity.
وجود الهوية المحلية.
And this is what the leaders of this region
وهذا ما يحاول قادة هذه
are trying to do.
المنطقة القيام به.
We're trying to be part of this global village,
نحن نحاول أن نكون جزءا من هذه القرية العالمية،
but at the same time we're revising ourselves
ولكن في الوقت نفسه نحن نراجع أنفسنا
through our cultural institutions and cultural development.
من خلال مؤسساتنا الثقافية والتنمية الثقافية.
I'm a representation of that phenomenon.
انا امثل هذه الظاهرة.
And I think a lot of people in this room,
واعتقد ان الكثير من الناس في هذه الغرفة،
I can see a lot of you are in the same position as myself.
أستطيع أن أرى الكثير منكم في نفس موقفي.
And I'm sure, although we can't see the people in Washington,
وأنا واثقة، على الرغم من أننا لا يمكن أن نرى الناس في واشنطن،
they are in the same position.
في نفس الموقف.
We're continuously trying to straddle
نحن نحاول باستمرار ان نقارب ما بين
different worlds, different cultures
مختلف العوالم والثقافات المختلفة
and trying to meet the challenges
ونحاول مواجهة التحديات
of a different expectation
لتوقعات مختلفة
from ourselves and from others.
من أنفسنا ومن الآخرين.
So I want to ask a question:
لذلك أريد أن أطرح سؤالا:
What should culture in the 21st century look like?
ما ينبغي للثقافة في القرن الـ 21 ان تبدو عليه؟
In a time where the world is becoming personalized,
في الوقت الذي اصبح فيه العالم شخصانيا،
when the mobile phone, the burger, the telephone,
عندما يكون الهاتف المحمول، و البرغر، الهاتف،
everything has its own personal identity,
كل شيء له هويته الشخصية،
how should we perceive ourselves
و الكيفية التي ننظر بها لأنفسنا
and how should we perceive others?
وكيف ينبغي أن نتصور الآخرين؟
How does that impact our desert culture?
كيف يمكن أن يأثر ذلك على ثقافتنا الصحراوية؟
I'm not sure of how many of you in Washington
لست متأكدا كم منكم في واشنطن
are aware of the cultural developments happening in the region
على بينة من التطورات الثقافية التي تجري في المنطقة
and, the more recent, Museum of Islamic Art
و، وأكثر حداثة، متحف الفن الإسلامي
opened in Qatar in 2008.
الذي افتتح في قطر في عام 2008.
I myself am personalizing these cultural developments,
أنا شخصيا اشخصن هذه التطورات الثقافية،
but I also understand
لكنني أدرك أيضا
that this has to be done organically.
أن هذا الذي ينبغي القيام به طبيعيا.
Yes, we do have all the resources that we need
نعم، لدينا جميع الموارد التي نحتاجها
in order to develop new cultural institutions,
من أجل تطوير مؤسسات ثقافية جديدة،
but what I think is more important
لكن ما أعتقد أنه أكثر أهمية
is that we are very fortunate
هو أننا محظوظون جدا
to have visionary leaders
أن يكون لدينا قادة ملهمين
who understand that this can't happen from outside,
يفهمون أن هذا لا يمكن أن يحدث من الخارج،
it has to come from within.
يجب ان يأتي من الداخل.
And guess what?
و خمنوا؟
You might be surprised to know that most people in the Gulf
قد تتفاجؤون أن تعرفوا أن معظم الناس في الخليج
who are leading these cultural initiatives
الذين يقودون هذه المبادرات الثقافية
happen to be women.
حدث أن يكن نساء.
I want to ask you, why do you think this is?
أريد أن أسألكم، ما هو السبب في اعتقادكم؟
Is it because it's a soft option;
هل لأنها خيار سهل؛
we have nothing else to do?
ليس لدينا شيء آخر للقيام به؟
No, I don't think so.
لا، أنا لا أعتقد ذلك.
I think that women in this part of the world
وأعتقد أن المرأة في هذا الجزء من العالم
realize that culture is an important component
أدركت أن الثقافة هي عنصر مهم
to connect people
لربط الناس
both locally and regionally.
على حد سواء محليا وإقليميا.
It's a natural component
انها عنصر طبيعي
for bringing people together, discussing ideas --
للتقريب بين الناس، ومناقشة الأفكار -
in the same way we're doing here at TED.
بنفس الطريقة التي نقوم به هنا في تيد.
We're here, we're part of a community,
نحن هنا، نحن جزء من هذا المجتمع،
sharing out ideas and discussing them.
نتبادل الأفكار و نناقشها.
Art becomes a very important part
الفن اصبح جزء مهم جدا
of our national identity.
من هويتنا الوطنية.
The existential and social and political impact
التأثير الوجودي والاجتماعي والسياسي
an artist has
الذي يملكه الفنان
on his nation's development of cultural identity
و دوره في تنمية الهوية الثقافية لأمته
is very important.
مهم جدا.
You know, art and culture is big business.
كما تعلمون، الفن والثقافة هي من الأعمال التجارية الكبيرة.
Ask me.
اسألوني.
Ask the chairpersons and CEOs
اسألوا رؤساء الشركات والمدراء التنفيذيين
of Sotheby's and Christie's.
من سوثبي وكريستي.
Ask Charles Saatchi about great art.
اسألوا تشارلز ساتشي عن الفن العظيم.
They make a lot of money.
لأنها تصنع الكثير من المال.
So I think women in our society
لذلك أعتقد أن النساء في مجتمعنا
are becoming leaders,
أصبحن قادة،
because they realize
لانهن يدركن
that for their future generations,
أن لأجيالهن في المستقبل،
it's very important
من المهم جدا
to maintain our cultural identities.
الحفاظ على هويتنا الثقافية.
Why else do Greeks demand the return
ولأي سبب آخر يطالب اليونانيون بعودة
of the Elgin Marbles?
رخامات إلجين؟
And why is there an uproar
ولماذا هناك ضجة
when a private collector tries to sell his collection
عندما يحاول أحد هواة الجمع بيع مجموعته
to a foreign museum?
إلى متحف أجنبي؟
Why does it take me months on end
لماذا يستغرقني أشهر
to get an export license from London or New York
الحصول على رخصة تصدير من لندن أو نيويورك
in order to get pieces into my country?
من أجل الحصول على قطع لبلدي؟
In few hours, Shirin Neshat, my friend from Iran
في ساعات قليلة، شيرين نشأت، صديقتي من إيران
who's a very important artist for us
و التي هي فنانة مهمة جدا بالنسبة لنا
will be talking to you.
وسوف تتحدث اليكم.
She lives in New York City, but she doesn't try to be a Western artist.
تعيش في مدينة نيويورك، لكنها لا تحاول أن تكون فنانة غربية.
Instead, she tries to engage
بدلا من ذلك، أنها تحاول الدخول
in a very important dialogue
في حوار مهم جدا
about her culture, nation and heritage.
حول ثقافة أمتها و تراثها.
She does that through important visual forms
فعلت ذلك من خلال أشكال بصرية هامة
of photography and film.
في التصوير الفوتوغرافي والسينما.
In the same way, Qatar is trying to grow its national museums
في نفس الاتجاه، قطر تحاول أن تنمي متاحفها الوطنية
through an organic process from within.
من خلال عملية طبيعية من الداخل.
Our mission is of cultural integration and independence.
مهمتنا تتضمن التكامل الثقافي والاستقلال.
We don't want to have what there is in the West.
نحن لا نريد ما يوجد في الغرب.
We don't want their collections.
نحن لا نريد مجموعاتهم.
We want to build our own identities, our own fabric,
نحن نريد أن نبني هويتنا الخاصة، والنسيج الخاص بنا،
create an open dialogue
خلق حوار مفتوح
so that we share our ideas
بحيث نتقاسم أفكارنا
and share yours with us.
ويتقاسم الغرب معنا.
In a few days,
في غضون أيام قليلة،
we will be opening the Arab Museum of Modern Art.
سيتم افتتاح المتحف العربي للفن الحديث.
We have done extensive research
قمنا ببحوث واسعة النطاق
to ensure that Arab and Muslim artists,
للتأكد من أن الفنانين العرب و المسلمين،
and Arabs who are not Muslims --
والعرب الذين ليسوا من المسلمين -
not all Arabs are Muslims, by the way --
ليس كل العرب مسلمين، بالمناسبة -
but we make sure that they are represented
لكننا نتأكد من أن يكونوا ممثلين
in this new institution.
في هذه المؤسسة الجديدة.
This institution is government-backed
هذه المؤسسة هي التي تدعمها الحكومة
and it has been the case
وكان من هذه القضية
for the past three decades.
على مدى العقود الثلاثة الماضية.
We will open the museum in a few days,
وسوف نفتح متحف في غضون أيام قليلة،
and I welcome all of you to get on Qatar Airways
وأنا أرحب بكم جميعا على متن خطوط الجوية القطرية
and come and join us.
لتأتوا وتنضموا إلينا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now this museum is just as important to us as the West.
الآن هذا المتحف لا يقل أهمية بالنسبة لنا كما في الغرب.
Some of you might have heard
قد سمعت البعض منكم
of the Algerian artist Baya Mahieddine,
بالفنانة الجزائرية باهيا محي الدين ،
but I doubt a lot of people know
ولكن أشك كثيرا من الناس يعرفون
that this artist worked in Picasso's studio
ان هذه الفنانة عملت في استوديو بيكاسو
in Paris in the 1930s.
في باريس في الثلاثينات.
For me it was a new discovery.
بالنسبة لي كان اكتشافا جديدا.
And I think with time, in the years to come
وأعتقد أنه مع مرور الوقت، في السنوات المقبلة
we'll be learning a lot about our Picassos,
سنتعلم الكثير عن فنانينا على شاكلة بيكاسو،
our Legers and our Cezannes.
و ليجيرس و سيزانس.
We do have artists,
لدينا فنانين،
but unfortunately we have not discovered them yet.
لكن لسوء الحظ أننا لم نكتشفهم حتى الآن.
Now visual expression is just one form
الآن التعبير البصري ليست سوى شكل واحد
of culture integration.
للتكامل الثقافي.
We have realized that recently
لقد أدركنا أنه في الآونة الأخيرة
more and more people
المزيد والمزيد من الناس
are using the means of YouTube and social networking
تستخدم وسائل تواصل الـ يوتيوب و الشبكات الاجتماعية
to express their stories, share their photos
للتعبير عن قصصهم، تبادل الصور
and tell their own stories through their own voices.
وسرد قصصهم الشخصية من خلال أصواتهم.
In a similar way,
بطريقة مماثلة،
we have created the Doha Film Institute.
انشأنا مهرجان معهد الدوحة للأفلام.
Now the Doha Film Institute is an organization
الآن معهد الدوحة للأفلام هي منظمة
to teach people about film and filmmaking.
لتعليم الناس السينما وصناعة الأفلام.
Last year we didn't have one Qatari woman filmmaker.
في العام الماضي لم يكن لدينا اي مخرجة قطرية.
Today I am proud to say
اليوم أنا فخورة بأن أقول
we have trained and educated
قمنا بتدريب وتعليم
over 66 Qatari women filmmakers
أكثر 66 من السينمائيات القطريات
to edit, tell their own stories
لتحرير وسرد قصصهم الشخصية
in their own voices.
بأصواتهن.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now if you'll allow me, I would love to share a one-minute film
الآن إذا كنتم تسمحوا لي، أحب أن اشارككم في فيلم مدته دقيقة واحدة
that has proven to show
قد اثبت ان إظهار
that a 60-sec film can be as powerful as a haiku
فيلم من 60 ثانية يمكن ان يكون قويا مثل الهايكو
in telling a big picture.
في التعبير بصورة كبيرة.
And this is one of our filmmakers' products.
وهذا هو واحد من المنتجات مخرجينا ".
(Video) Boy: Hey listen! Did you know that the stocks are up?
(فيديو) ولد: اسمع! هل تعلم أن الأسهم في صعود؟
Who are you playing?
مع من كنت تلعب؟
Girl: Uncle Khaled. Here, put on the headscarf.
فتاة: العم خالد. هنا، وضع الحجاب.
Khaled: Why would I want to put it on?
خالد: لماذا علي أضعه؟
Girl: Do as you're told, young girl.
فتاة: افعلي كما قلت لك، فتاة صغيرة.
Boy: No, you play mom and I play dad. (Girl: But it's my game.)
الصبي: لا، انت تلعبي دور أمي و انا العب دور أبي. (فتاة: ولكن هذه لعبتي)
Play by yourself then.
اذن العبي لوحدك.
Girl: Women! One word and they get upset.
فتاة: النساء! كلمة واحدة تضايقهن.
Useless.
عديم الفائدة.
Thank you. Thank you!
شكرا لكم. شكرا لكم!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
SM: Going back to straddling between East and West,
ش م: وبالعودة الى التداخل بين الشرق والغرب،
last month we had our second Doha Tribeca Film Festival
في الشهر الماضي كان لدينا مهرجان الدوحة السينمائي الثاني لترايبكا
here in Doha.
هنا في الدوحة.
The Doha Tribeca Film Festival
مهرجان الدوحة السينمائي ترايبيكا
was held at our new cultural hub, Katara.
عُقد في المركز الثقافي الجديد، كتارا.
It attracted 42,000 people,
استقطب 42،000 نسمة،
and we showcased 51 films.
وعرضنا 51 فيلما.
Now the Doha Tribeca Film Festival
الآن في الدوحة ترايبيكا السينمائي
is not an imported festival,
ليس مهرجانا مستوردا،
but rather an important festival
بل هو مهرجان تعاوني مهم
between the cities of New York and Doha.
بين مدينتي نيويورك والدوحة.
It's important for two things.
مهم لأمرين.
First, it allows us to showcase
أولا، لأنها تتيح لنا عرض
our Arab filmmakers and voices
السينمائيين العرب والأصوات
to one of the most cosmopolitan cities in the world,
في واحدة من أكثر المدن عالمية في العالم،
New York City.
مدينة نيويورك.
At the same time, we are inviting them
في الوقت نفسه، نحن ندعوهم
to come and explore our part of the world.
ليأتوا لاستكشاف هذا الجزء من العالم.
They're learning our culture, our language, our heritage
انهم يتعلمون ثقافتنا ولغتنا وتراثنا
and realizing we're just as different
و يدركوا كما اننا مختلفين
and just the same as each other.
في نفس الوقت نحن متشابهين.
Now over and over again,
الآن مرارا وتكرارا،
people have said, "Let's build bridges,"
يقول الناس "دعونا نبني الجسور"،
and frankly, I want to do more than that.
وبصراحة، أريد أن أفعل أكثر من ذلك.
I would like break the walls of ignorance
أرغب في كسر جدران الجهل
between East and West --
بين الشرق والغرب -
no, not the soft option that we have discussed before,
لا، ليس الخيار السهل الذي ناقشناه من قبل،
but rather the soft power
ولكن القوة الناعمة
that Joseph Nye has spoken about before.
التي تحدث عنها جوزيف ناي من قبل.
Culture's a very important tool to bring people together.
الثقافة أداة مهمة جدا لجمع الناس معا.
We should not underestimate it.
لا ينبغي لنا أن نقلل من ذلك.
"Know thyself,"
"اعرف ذاتك"
that is the journey of self-expression and self-realization
تلك هي رحلة للتعبير عن الذات وتحقيق الذات
that we are traveling.
التي نمضي عبرها .
Now I don't pretend to have all the answers,
الآن وأنا لا أدعي أني املك كل الأجوبة،
but I know that me as an individual
ولكني أعلم أني كفرد
and we as a nation
ونحن كأمة
welcome this community
نرحب بهذا المجتمع
of ideas worth spreading.
للأفكار التي تستحق الإنتشار.
This is a very interesting journey.
هذه هي رحلة مثيرة جدا للاهتمام.
I welcome you on board
أرحب بكم على متنها
for us to engage and discuss new ideas
لمشاركتنا و مناقشة الأفكار الجديدة
of how to bring people together
عن كيفية جمع الناس معا
through cultural initiatives and discussions.
من خلال المبادرات الثقافية والمناقشات.
Familiarity destroys and trumps fear. Try it.
معرفتنا وإلمامنا ببعض يدمر و يطرد الخوف. حاولوا ذلك.
Ladies and gentlemen, thank you very much. Shokran.
سيداتي وسادتي، شكرا جزيلا. شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)